[Music]
dates are one of the healthiest
sweeteners
that's what we use the how not to die
cookbook
you can blend them with water and make
date syrup or use date sugar which is a
whole food just dried dates ground into
powder and as such is packed with
nutrition ending up with as much
antioxidant power as blackstrap molasses
but without the strong taste
though not all brands are the same for
example bob's red mill may have twice
the antioxidants compared to now foods
though they only tested one package each
okay so dates are healthy compared to
other sweeteners
that's not saying much do dates have any
special medicinal properties
you'll see papers like this in the
medical literature touting the
therapeutic effects of date fruits and
the prevention of diseases
anti-inflammatory antioxidant anti-tumor
activity complete with figures like this
of the purported pharmacological
activities of date fruits in disease
control but what they don't say is some
of this may be based on studies like
this where they feed dates to rats that
sounds nice
but then induce testicular ischemia by
twisting their left testicle clockwise
720 degrees so like two full rotations
to completely kink off the blood
supply so did the dates help
who cares if the dates helped we're
talking about rat testicles
it's like when researchers test the nut
on nut effects of pecans what relevance
does that have so ironically
perhaps the strangest assertion here
that dates helps with labor and delivery
is actually supported by randomized and
double-blind placebo-controlled trials
as i've covered before so
let's keep an open mind here what about
the purported anti-cancer effects
researchers studied the impact of dates
on our good gut flora and colon cancer
cell proliferation our gut harbors about
10 000 billion microorganisms and is
considered the most metabolically active
site in the human body all sorts of
crazy stuff is happening down there and
we can reward our good gut flora by
feeding them prebiotics like dietary
fiber and polyphenols a class of
antioxidant phytonutrients and dates
have high levels of both so let's blend
up some dates with some gut flora fecal
slurries donated by volunteers you've
heard of green smoothies more like a
brown smoothie well
what happened
both the whole date extract and just the
date polyphenols were able to
significantly increase the growth of
beneficial bacteria and then they also
assessed the ability of mixtures to
inhibit the growth of colon cancer cells
in a petri dish even just a polyphenol
fraction cut cancer cell growth by more
than half and the whole date extract
nearly blocked cancer cell growth
completely
together these data suggest that
consumption of dates may enhance colon
health by increasing beneficial
bacterial growth and inhibiting the
proliferation of colon cancer cells
it would have been nice if they actually
studied the effects of dates in the
actual colon but there's never been such
a study
until
now the impact of date consumption on
gut flora growth and large intestinal
health at randomized controlled
crossover human interventional study
volunteers were randomized to either a
control group or seven dates a day for
three weeks and there were significant
increases in bowel movement frequency
not surprising eating the additional
fiber but also
significant reductions in stool ammonia
concentrations after consuming dates i
have a video on why that's important
furthermore date intake significantly
reduced genotoxicity
in human fecal water
what the heck is that that's like human
stool tea a water extract of feces from
someone eating seven dates a day
causes significantly less genotoxicity
meaning is significantly less dna
damaging which is good since that's
what's coating the insides of our colon
on a daily basis dozens of different
date varieties have been pitted no pun
intended against a variety of cancer
cells in vitro and not just colon cancer
and stomach cancer which the dates might
actually come in contact with but also
prostate cancer cells lung and breast
cancer cells but of course we'd have to
for show that the active components are
actually absorbed into the bloodstream
and end up in those organs
[Music]
i